[Uhtred] My name is Uhtred,
son of Uhtred.
I was born a Saxon,
but stolen, and raised as a Dane.
But now I find myself
bound to King Alfred.
And bound
by marriage to Wessex.
I have a Christian wife,
whom I care for.
[baby crying]
And I child I have never seen.
I have land,
burdened with debt.
It is a substantial amount,
Lord.
Alfred could remove the debt,
but he has chosen not to.
[Uhtred] And a sly servant
I cannot trust.
And though I miss
the ways of the Danes,
and their hunger for life
and for battle.
Never cross Ubba.
And never, never fight him.
[Uhtred] Fate has stirred
my Saxon heart for a reason.
[man] Ubba and his army
have returned from Ireland.
And my fleet is where?
[man] They left Lundene several
days ago and are nearly here, Lord.
[Uhtred] Destiny is all.
[thunder rumbles]
[horse whinnies]
[Oswald]
Lord?
When will you need assistance?
[baby crying]
Mildrith!
-Odda?
-Mildrith. Thank, God.
-What are you doing here?
-You must come with me.
The peace is over.
We are under siege.
Since when?
You must gather
all you need and quickly.
The Danes could
be here at any time.
-I cannot go with you.
-Yes, you can. You must.
If the peace is over,
then what of Uhtred?
Mildrith, the Danes
have broken the truce.
We have killed
all the hostages given to us
and they will
have done the same.
If Uhtred has survived,
it can only be as a traitor,
a Dane!
No.
Regardless, it is no longer
safe for you here,
-you must come with me.
-[thunder rumbles]
Mildrith! I beg you,
for the sake of your child.
Do not worry about us lady,
we'll get ourselves and the
livestock to the hills.
Get yourself
clear of this place.
Anything of value I will bury!
[birds squawking]
[indistinct chatter]
[man] Don't just pull at the
bugger, you'll have it torn!
-Find out what holds it!
-[Uhtred] How much for your horse?
He's not for sale.
I'll give you
twice its worth. In silver.
Have any washed up alive?
Not on my beach.
God's taken hundreds
of the bastards.
Though it's said hundreds more have
landed safely, further up the shore.
Friends of yours?
You should
take your families to safety.
-Ertwit?
-He has your look, definitely.
Little Ertwit. Little Ertwit.
[chuckles]
Let's hope he does not
develop my constitution.
[door opens]
They are here.
Shh, shh, shh...
Odda? Wulfhere?
[both] Lord.
Difficult times,
which we will face head on.
Never rest.
Do we march as one Lord,
or are we to split?
We are split.
You both shall ride towards
the Severn River to face Ubba.
I shall ride south
to face Guthrum.
Should we not all be marching
to the Severn lord?
If this first battle is won,
then the Danes may not
care for a second.
Wulfhere, even in victory
we can never be sure
of our surviving numbers.
Some of Guthrum's ships
will of made it to shore,
and I can not let him simply
walk through Wessex;
he must be faced.
Odda, should either of us
have luck
and defeat our enemy quickly,
we will march to the others aid.
Yes, Lord, of course.
Prepare...
[cows mooing]
[chickens clucking]
[man grunting]
By God, girl, you are a lovely
field to plough.
A lovely field to plough.
Better than barley...
[grunts]
By God, girl,
better than barley!
Better than barley, yeah,
[screams]
Better than barley!
Lord! Lord! Forgive, Lord,
it's never happened before,
I swear it'll never
happen again.
-It was the girl's idea.
-It was not!
-Where's my wife?
-It was not my idea at--
-Where is my wife and child?
-Wait! Wait! Lord!
She's with
Lord Odda the Younger.
-Odda?
-Yes, Lord.
He took the lady and your son.
She went willingly,
Lord, to protect the child.
-My son?
-Yes, Lord, you have a son.
Handsome little man he is.
Looks like his father.
I should really take your balls
for this, desecration.
Yes... No, Lor... Please.
I do not care for you;
your wife,
your children nor your whore.
Lord, he made me do it,
with the promise of a coin.
It was false promise, Lord,
I have no coin.
I will need a fresh horse,
food and drink.
Yes, Lord. Your own horse was
returned, it's in the stable.
My house is not your house.
No, Lord.
I beg your pardon, Lord.
My land is not your land.
Treat me as a fool again
and I'll kill you.
Yes, Lord.
I'll enjoy it.
I believe you would.
Leave me.
Uhtred... son of Uhtred...
We outnumber them I feel.
[Leofric]
We outnumber them if you count
the farm boys and women, Lord.
You fear them, Leofric?
I do not. Though some do.
It is not about fear,
it is about strategy.
We hold the high ground;
they must come to us.
And if they
decide to wait, Lord?
Why would they?
Because we are sat isolated
on this high ground.
[Wulfhere] And supplies are low.
They don't know that!
We bide our time.
Hold our position.
With luck,
Alfred will see off Guthrum,
and provide us
with reinforcements.
For now we stay put... on this hill.
[indistinct chatter]
Lord...
They are gathering,
and they are watching.
They have the higher ground.
But I do not want to wait.
So... when do I attack?
I'll cast the runes.
Storri,
I will need a clear answer.
I will get one.
[spits]
I have your answer, Lord.
Look, this is us
at the base of their hill,
they sit on top,
but that's not an advantage.
This is a feather from that
camp, bone dry and faded.
Water runs down the hill,
not up.
You have your wish, Lord,
an early attack is good.
They're weak.
They will surrender or die,
and then we move into
the heart of Wessex.
Shield wall!
Advance!
-One! Two!
-[men grunt in unison]
-[man] Horsemen approaching!
-Halt.
[yelling in distance]
Go and fetch, Lord Odda...
...the Elder!
It is Uhtred...
How could he have lived?
We will ask.
Aelderman Uhtred,
we feared you'd been killed!
That you were not is a miracle,
or something less godly.
[grunting]
-Where is she?
-What? What?
Where's my wife and child?
-She... she's safe!
-You brought her here?!
She is safe!
Did you not hear him!?
She is safe! I took her
to safety, nothing more!
Mildrith is with my own wife!
On my land, in my house!
Where she has lived
happily in the past!
Put away your dagger!
Swear that you haven't
laid a hand on her.
-I will do no such thing!
-Swear!
Lord you will take your blade
away from my Lord
and you will do it now.
Arseling!
You have my word that neither Mildrith
nor your son have been harmed.
I swear, do as I ask.
[panting]
Treason...
but what can we expect.
Enough, this in-fighting
and argument!
Disperse... all of you! Now!
Your wife remains
my goddaughter.
You should be thanking my son,
not threatening him!
Now come to me
when your thinking is clear.
And you explain to me why you are
still breathing... and stupid!
You are back from the dead
and unchanged.
All you had to do
was get down from your horse
and ask,
"Have you seen my wife?"
That would have been
the better choice, yes,
but then Young Odda
wouldn't have shit himself.
[both laughing]
You seen her? She's well?
She is well.
The child, however...
-Sickly?
-Ugly.
Like his father?
Worse... with the smallest
of pebbles for a penis.
Like his father.
[chuckling]
If you wish to see him
for yourself, Arseling,
I say you leave
the way you came.
I'm serious.
We are stuck on
this hill and here we will die.
What does Odda say?
Odda is a decent man,
but as a warrior,
he has all the guile
and menace of a sheep.
[Odda the Elder]
We have the ground; the slope...
I will not surrender
that advantage.
But if food is scarce, Lord,
how long can we wait?
We shall find food!
We have food for how many days?
Two, three, four?
Enough time
for Alfred to arrive.
You yourself have reported
that the storm has taken
most of Guthrum's ships.
-But not all.
-But enough, perhaps...
So we wait. Mm?
Agreed, for a time.
We give Alfred
as much time as possible.
I will offer negotiations,
and while those negotiations
are taking place
we will send out
hunting parties, several.
Alfred will come.
I'll attend
these negotiations with Ubba.
You have not been invited.
It's my right.
If the other hostages
were killed, how did he survive?
He was taken as a child
by the Danes and he survived.
We would do well to follow him.
Follow him?
Or listen to what he has to say,
Lord, is what I meant.
Lord Ubba, may I present
the Lord Odda of Wessex.
There never seems to be a
meeting that you do not attend.
Is there more than one of you?
Lord Ubba, Odda's Alfred's
most trusted general.
[scoffs]
I don't give a shit who he is,
all he needs to do is to surrender.
There will be no surrender.
[chuckles]
What will there be?
There will be no surrender.
Though I do invite you
to return to your ships.
Guthrum may have
broken the peace,
but there's no need
for Ubba to do likewise.
We will not be
returning to our ships.
And I shall not be moving
from this hill.
[chuckles]
You have
no business in Wessex.
My business is to kill you.
-You may try.
-Guthrum's fleet's gone.
Njord reached out from the deep
and dragged Guthrum's fleet
down to the sea-bed.
You're lying.
I watched the fleet die
and its men go under!
Storri, what do you say?!
Lord, I do not see for Guthrum,
I... I see for you.
Storri is a man who wears
a stick up his arse,
he didn't
see that coming either.
No, that... that's a lie.
It's all lies! Look at his eyes!
You are next to die, Ubba,
and I know it, I cast the runes.
That's an even bigger lie.
Earl Ragnar the Fearless
is with the Gods
and they are angry at you;
you allow his death
to go unpunished.
Avenging Earl Ragnar
is not my business!
That's for his son!
You're next to die, Ubba.
[yells]
Then fight me! And you'll see
who is next to die! Fight me!
Lord... we're negotiating.
You will not say another word!
He will not say another word!
He will not, no. Best not.
I will not say another word.
Talking is over.
You piece of weasel shit!
Storri! Storri!
[exhales]
What now?
Where we left standing? In shit?
Now we have time.
How? If it were possible,
you've made them
want to kill us even more!
We should attack.
[indistinct chatter]
[men laughing]
[Odda the Elder]
My men are good men.
Though half of them are armed only
with reaping hooks, they're here.
Reaping hooks can kill.
How well do you know Ubba?
I've known Ubba
since I was 11-years-old.
He is the greatest warrior
I have ever seen,
but he's cautious, he listens
to the gods, always.
I goaded him
only to make him doubt.
It will take a little while
for the doubt to clear,
you have your time, but I say again,
we should attack.
If we attack
we will be outflanked,
my men die, all of them.
I know each of them.
I'd hoped this hill and Alfred
might save them... us.
Alfred won't come.
The food won't last,
and Ubba's mind will clear.
It seems inevitable,
they will take Wessex.
What if we were able
to outflank the Danes?
How?
We burn their ships.
Even if it's just three or four,
they'd be running to the fire.
-Then we attack.
-They'll be disorganized.
No shield wall.
We could be killing them
before they know we're there.
Who would set the fires?
I will. Alone.
But I'll need your word
that you'll attack as soon
as the fires have taken hold.
You have it.
If we succeed, Lord,
you'll have saved Wessex.
If he succeeds,
fires the ships,
it will undoubtedly cause panic
amongst the Danes.
Which is the aim.
How best do we use that panic?
Is an attack
likely to be successful?
Would it not be better
to escape this hill?
We can return to Winchester
without the loss
of a single man.
Excepting Uhtred.
Father, if what Uhtred says
about the storm is true,
and Guthrum's fleet
is all but destroyed,
we would
join forces with Alfred;
we may well meet him
on the road.
Then we are all against Ubba.
As a strategy it makes sense.
I gave him my word.
He will die,
and you can call him a hero.
The others are here, you must
decide what you will tell them.
I have called for you,
to tell you to ready your men;
all men. Everyone.
-We shall be moving... soon.
-Moving, Lord?
Aelderman Uhtred, has volunteered
himself to distract the Danes.
He will endeavor to set alight
a number of their ships.
-He has gone?
-Yes.
-Alone?
If he should succeed
in causing this distraction,
we will move.
In which direction, Lord?
Ready your men;
tell them nothing.
Lord Odda, with respect,
you told us nothing.
I have told you
to ready your men.
-Ready for battle?
-Ready your men, each of you.
Go! Prepare!
[indistinct chatter]
[laughing]
[grunts]
I see nothing on the river.
-It will soon be first light.
-Can you not speak?
Very well.
[flames cackling]
Ships afire! Ships afire!
[indistinct shouting]
Fetch buckets and barrels!
[men yelling]
Lord Odda, we are ready,
but to do what?
He's done it.
Look, he's fired the ships.
We attack!
Lord? Lord you awake?
-Lord!
-What?
The ships have been fired!
[groans]
-It's him, I know it!
-Yes.
You saw them dying on the hill!
Did you not see a fire?!
I told you I can only see
what the runes allow!
-How many ships burn?
-I don't know. Many.
They are planning something,
they must be.
Lord... there.
That's him.
You! Uhtred Ragnarson! You!
Are you afraid of me?
Man on man,
I will make the square.
Will you fight me?
Are you the son of
Ragnar the Fearless?
Or are you a coward?!
I will fight you Ubba,
if that's what you want,
but you will die.
Fetch him a shield.
You are half naked, Lord,
you might catch a chill.
This will not take long.
Was it you? The fires?
Must have been the gods...
they're angry with you.
First blood or to the death?
-[yells]
-[all yelling]
[grunting]
Get up! Get up!
[groans in pain]
[yells indistinct]
[grunts]
[shouts in pain]
Go to Valhalla, Lord...
[grunts]
[panting]
[Leofric]
Shield... wall!
-Now kill the bastards!
-[all shouting]
[birds squawking]
[Odda the Younger]
Tie them...
Tie them all together,
form a chain.
Bind them tightly.
If any object,
march them into the river.
Get this
inside your belly, arseling.
God knows you deserve it.
Lord Odda is hurt... badly.
He kept his word.
He would, he is a good man;
a good Aelderman.
I want Ubba buried
with his axe.
His axe is gone.
Young Odda wants him
cut into pieces.
-No, that can't happen.
-He would have done the same to you.
He is Ubba, as close as the
Danes will ever come to a king.
I'll see he's buried.
You, you have a task ahead.
You go directly to Alfred
and you kneel at his feet.
And tell the bastard
you have saved Wessex.
No, I'll go to Mildrith.
If you don't do it, some other bugger
will, and there will be reward.
Men have seen it,
they know what I have done,
let them tell Alfred.
I need to see my son.
You're a turd. A ball bag.
Is that the best you can do?
Nipple.
Lord... I want to thank you
for not abandoning me.
I know that would have been
a choice, a reasonable choice.
I'll go to your estate now,
to see Mildrith and my son.
You served Alfred well, today.
Thank you, Lord.
[birds chirping]
[branch cracks]
Who's there?
[gasps]
Forgive me, you looked
too beautiful to disturb.
[giggles]
You may disturb me...
immediately.
Uhtred, son of Uhtred.
Who is the son of another
Uhtred... and another.
He has a kingdom to inherit.
I will see that it happens.
Tomorrow or the day after we go
home and then to Winchester,
the three of us, yes.
I'll go to Alfred,
and he will fall at my feet.
-He will?
-He will.
Oh...
-[baby farts]
-[both chuckles]
He'll free us of our debt,
at the very least.
And we will build a great hall
and hold a feast.
I'd like that.
And I'd like Uhtred to be
baptized... in Winchester.
Father Beocca could perform
the ceremony. He'd be pleased.
Uhtred, it's what I want.
God is good Uhtred.
He kept you safe;
he brought you home to me.
My sword kept me safe.
Believe me... God is good.
They've not yet gone to battle.
This is good.
I alone will speak.
Alfred is to hear
one clear message.
How is the mood... in the camp?
It's good, Lord.
The men are well.
Afraid?
No, no more than is usual.
I...
I worry that I do not
inspire them;
that they do not
see me as a warrior.
Lord...
Lord it is Odda.
What is this?
Young Odda? You have news?
Where is your father?
He was wounded in battle;
a great battle at Cynuit, Lord.
Lord, I have a gift for you.
Ubba is dead;
his army is defeated.
This is... This is true?
-It is Lord. Two days ago.
-[Beocca] Praise God; praise him.
[soft chuckle]
Well, then Wessex is saved.
It is, uh, for a time.
Guthrum will have no choice now,
but to make peace.
While your father recovers,
you will stand in his place;
his lands will be
your lands and more.
[both chuckle]
Wessex is saved.
[indistinct chatter]
Everybody is walking
to the palace.
A celebration, it must be...
a celebration of prayers.
I believe you did this.
The great hall is now full,
there is no more room.
Please, the King thanks you
all for coming,
but you need to pray here,
outside.
-[Uhtred] Father Beocca.
-The palace is full.
Father Beocca...
[Beocca] There will be ale and
food available for everyone.
Uhtred?
-You are here before me now?
-I am, and with my child.
Oh, God be praised.
You are alive!
Of course, I'm alive,
why shouldn't I be alive?
You were at Werham, a hostage,
we thought you were dead.
No, Father, I was at Cynuit,
I fought at Cynuit.
Did they not say?
-I'll see Alfred now!
-What is it?
Nothing I'm sure that cannot
be resolved given time. Uhtred!
I'll see Alfred.
Uh... nah,
Uhtred, Alfred is at peace!
Uhtred, please!
Uhtred, please,
you cannot disturb prayers!
Uhtred! Uhtred, your sword!
Forgive me, but I am told
that you believe me dead?
Uhtred this is not the time.
Father Beocca here
believed me dead,
and yet just days ago I was with
at Cynuit with Lord Odda.
It was Lord Odda and I who
devised our battle plan.
-Did the boy not say?
-Uhtred, stop now.
Perhaps you'd like to speak now?
Odda, you will say nothing.
Perhaps you would like to
describe Ubba's death?
Lord, I would like to invite
the Aelderman here to join us,
in giving thanks and prayer.
Giving thanks for what,
for victory?
For the death of the Pagan?
Who do you think
killed the Pagan?
I cannot save you.
I fought Ubba, man-on-man
and I killed him!
It was his axe
against my sword, this sword!
[crowd gasps]
Is there any man here
who will deny it?
Be still! Everyone!
Be still and be silent!
I have heard enough.
You have said enough.
This is not seemly...
Now sheath your sword
and remember where you stand.
Lord, what I'm saying to you...
You have broken my peace.
You have broken the peace of Christ
and you have brought weapons into a
sacred place.
Lord, I'm telling you
the truth--
You will go directly
to the courtyard
and you will wait for me
to pass judgment.
Judgment? For what?
I have done nothing wrong--
You will be quiet!
We will, um...
We will continue
with a moment of silence...
...to help find
the peace once more.
This interruption cannot
be allowed to go unpunished.
It must be death.
Peace be with you, my dear.
Why are you unable to reason?
To show patience?
All I expect is justice.
And it comes...
to those who have faith.
Now is not the time
to talk of faith.
Now is precisely the time,
now is when it's needed.
I'll have none of it!
You're too ready with anger.
There's a bad spirit within you
that needs to be exorcised.
You should look to God.
I'll pray for you.
Humility is what you need.
What I need, woman, is justice.
[snoring]
[groans]
[sighs]
You sober?
Delicate.
You are to grovel.
[groans]
What again?
With me.
All I did
was abscond from a monastery.
-Aelderman Wulfhere.
-You know this wretch, I believe?
We've met.
The king has sent me
to punish you;
along with Aethelwold here.
What his wife would like is for me to
pull your guts through your smelly arse.
Aelswith is forever inventive.
Lady, you are
to go to Aelswith, for comfort.
She waits in the chapel.
Do you know
what the punishment is
for drawing your sword
before the King?
A fine:
payable to the church no doubt?
Death.
But Alfred is feeling merciful;
you will not dangle, not today.
He wants your assurance
you will keep the peace.
-What peace?
-His peace, you fool!
It does not matter a gnat's dick
that you killed Ubba.
What matters is that Odda the
Younger has claimed the credit.
Should his father die
from his wounds,
Odda becomes one of
the richest men in Wessex
and men will want
to praise his bravery.
-My bravery.
-Not a gnat's dick.
The sun now shines from Odda
the Younger's arsehole,
and it is blinding.
Do you understand me?
Good.
You are to do penance?
To do what?
Grovel...
You are to dress like a girl,
go on your knees
and be humiliated.
I won't grovel.
Then Aelswith gets her wish,
and I pull your guts
through your arse...
Which will it be?
On your knees.
[indistinct chatter
and laughter]
Now you will crawl,
all the way to the palace,
where you will kiss the cross
and lie flat down on your face.
And then what?
God and the king
will forgive you.
Go.
[crowd laughing]
Go!
[woman] That's what you get!
[yells]
I will lead, but you owe me.
What?
Oh...
Oh, Lord I am a sinner,
do not look at me.
[man] You are!
I am a sinner Lord,
as big a sinner
as you will ever see!
I have known women, Lord!
Lots and lots of women.
[man] Lucky, bugger.
[crowd laughing]
Women of all sizes:
The big tits, small tits,
I have squeezed and...
and kissed them all.
I have rested my head
on the bosoms of beautiful
but bad, bad women Lord,
forgive me!
I... I have lost count of
the number of women I have had,
but I know it is exactly
half the number
of tits I have caressed!
[crowd laughing]
Oh, God. I love tits!
Send me an angel, Lord!
So you can hump her?
[stuttering]
A titless angel to guide me.
No more servant girls in my bed
chamber, Lord, please...
I beg you.
[crowd cheering]
You must lay flat
and kiss the cross.
Kiss my arse...
you and your God.
-Uhtred... Uhtred, stop!
-We are leaving this place.
We can't.
We are leaving.
Collect your belongings.
It will be dark soon,
and there's the baptism.
-It is important.
-My son will not be baptized.
No priest will whisper
lies and deceit into his ears
and half drown him in water!
Stop it,
stop it you are angry, shh!
He will be a Pagan,
like his father!
Why are you saying this?
We will stay tonight,
no longer.
I will find you
in the morning.
Where are you going?
Drinking... and whoring...
I love tits!
[men laughing]
And we appreciate
the finer points of the tit,
the smaller tits,
the manageable tit,
the perk eager delighted tit,
the soft enveloping tit, the tit
that makes you feel at home,
like a puppies nose, grateful,
eager, receptive to touch.
How are your knees?
I can't laugh about it...
There's no justice here.
Only the church.
You knew that.
I here you're now
Young Odda's man now.
I'm passed from father to son,
yes, like the land.
I can't stay in Wessex.
You have a wife. A child
you could not wait to see.
Where would you go?
Odda is afraid
that you will kill him.
Tell him I might.
Tell him each night,
before he goes to bed.
[chuckles]
I need to find wealth,
but here it's impossible.
Danes, they would see it
and take it.
And that is what we do.
We become Danes
and we'll plunder.
Men will follow you.
Those men we have schooled;
others who were at Cynuit,
they will follow you.
You're saying that we raid?
We find wealth and we take it.
Here in Wessex?
No, you do not shit
at your own table; Cornwalum.
We take it from the Britons.
Do not say yes,
not yet, think...
I'll do the same.
But why should Odda
be rewarded and not us?
Lord... Welcome.
I was not expecting you
home so soon.
Did the baptism go well?
It's a fine tree.
-Good day, lady.
-A miserable day.
[Uhtred]
Where was it felled, this tree?
On the top ridge, Lord.
On my land?
Yes, Lord. I am taking it
to Wigulf's Mill, for splitting.
He buys it?
He splits it, Lord.
We need...
We need timber for repairs.
He takes his payments
in split wood.
If we need timber,
why not split it ourselves?
Wigulf has always done it, Lord.
So if I go to Wigulf,
he will tell me how many such
trees he has split.
And you will show me the timber.
How much is a tree
like this worth?
Eight, nine shillings?
I'm not certain, Lord.
How much does he
pay you for my timber?
Lord, it is one tree.
How much does he pay you?
Lady, please.
How much does he
pay you for my timber?
-Uhtred, no!
-You be quiet!
Uhtred!
[grunting]
-[horse whinnies]
-Uhtred!
[screams]
[groans in pain]
[gasps for air]
[panting]
That... was justice!